Guide to the Marie Corelli Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marie Corelli collection
1885-1947
GEN MSS 332
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.1
(5 boxes)
Collection includes letters between Corelli and her publishers, George and Richard Bentley, 1885-1894, including a copy of a letter by Basil Wilberforce concerning Corelli's "Barabbas"; letters to Alexander Wedderburn, 1908-17, that discuss John Ruskin, Arthur and Joan Severn, and personal matters; letters between George Bentley, Eric Mackay, and Arthur Waugh; autograph manuscript of "The Great Secret" (published in 1920 as "The Secret Power"); and a corrected typescript by Bertha Vyver entitled "Marie Corelli" (published in 1930 as "Memoirs of Marie Corelli") that contains a chapter by John Cuming Walters.
Corelli, Marie, 1855-1924
Vyver, Bertha
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Source information is recorded in series level notes. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Marie Corelli, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to February 1998 have been organized into three series: Series I, Ray Livingston Murphy Bequest, Series II, Charles J. Levy Gift, and Series III, Materials from Other Sources, which consists of material acquired from various other sources.
Memoirs of Marie Corelli; The great secret; The secret power; Bentley, George, 1828-1895; Bentley, R. (Richard), 1854-1936; Corelli, Marie, 1855-1924; Mackay, Eric, 1851-1898; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Severn, Arthur, 1842-1931; Severn, Joan, 1846-1924; Walters, John Cuming, 1933-; Waugh, Arthur, 1866-1943; Wedderburn, Alexander D. O. (Alexander Dundas Ogilvy), 1854-1931; Wilberforce, Basil, 1841-1916
- Ray Livingston Murphy Bequest, 1885-1947, n.d.; Series I; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Bequest of Ray Livingston Murphy, 1954
  - CORRESPONDENCE OF MARIE CORELLI
    - Correspondence with George Bentley, 1885-91 (Box 1, Folder 1-25)
    - Correspondence with George Bentley, 1892-94, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26-37)
    - Letters to Richard Bentley, 1889-92 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      It is possible that other 1889 letters are intended for Richard, rather than George; Richard was actually running the business at the time because of his father's ill health. Letter of [ca. Nov 20] 1893 includes copy of letter from Basil Wilberforce concerning Corelli's book Barabbas
    - Correspondence with Bentley & Son, 1889-92 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - ALS from Billing & Sons, 1892 Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - ALS copy to Mary Scott, 1886 Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - ALS copy to "M. K. B.", 1887 Feb 18 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 2 ALS (copies) from to "admirers", 1886 Nov 10 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - 1 ALS, on stationary of the Constitutional Club, from "An old friend of R. B. Co." [MC?] to the firm, [n.y.] Tues (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Correspondence between Eric MacKay (Marie's half-brother) and George Bentley, 1892 Feb-May (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
    - AL signed "The Editor" from The Novel Review to George Bentley, [1892] Apr 14 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - ALS from Arthur Waugh to George Bentley, 1892 Feb 29 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - 2 autographs clipped from letters, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - 1 page of notes about 2 Corelli letters. In an unidentified hand (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1892-1947, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Charles J. Levy Gift, 1904-1924; Series II; 0.4; (1 box)
  Gift of Charles J. Levy, 1976
  - ALS to Mrs. Sidney Gladstone. Stratford-on-Avon, 1904 Nov 27 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - 3 ALS to unidentified recipients. Stratford-on-Avon, 1905-24, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Autograph clipped from a letter, 1905 Jun 28 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - The Great Secret, autograph manuscript of a novel, ca. 1920 (Box 3, Folder 55-71)
    Published in 1920 as The Secret Power. Presentation inscription on the title page to Bertha Vyver
- Materials from Other Sources, 1890-1930, n.d.; Series III; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources, as indicated on individual folders.
  - Letters to Alexander Dundas Ogilvy Wedderburn, 1908-17 (Box 4, Folder 72-87)
    Letters discuss John Ruskin, Arthur Severn and Joan Severn, and miscellaneous personal details
    Letter of Dec. 7, 1909 includes carbon of poem entitled "Rosalind" signed by MC; letter of Mar. 2, 1913 includes carbon of a letter to [Mr. Freeman]; Letter of Nov. 22, 1915 includes carbon of poem entitled "The Ballad of Edward Grey" by MC
    Includes: Harvard House Gazette and American Visitors' Chronicle, Stratford-on-Avon, October 1909
  - ALS to Mr[?] Courtney, Longridge Road, Earl's Court, S.W., 1895 Nov 16 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - ALS to Miss Curtis, Longridge Road, Earl's Court, S.W., [n.y.] Sun (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - ALS to Mssrs. Lindley Jones and brother, Stratford-on-Avon, 1910 Feb 10 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - ALS to William Kean Seymour, Stratford-on-Avon, 1918 Nov 12 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - ALS to Mr. O'Connor, [London], 1892 Mar 24 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - 3 ALS to "Annie", 1890-91 (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - ALS to "Dear Sir," Mason Croft, Stratford-on-Avon, 1901 Jan 5 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - ALS to "My Dear Sir," Cannes, 1894 Jan 31 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - ANS to an unidentified recipient, Mason Croft, Stratford-on-Avon, Warwickshire, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Note in an unidentified hand, 1898 Jun 7 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Printed thank-you note to unidentified recipient, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 98)
  - Marie Corelli, by Bertha Vyver. Typescript with corrections in the author's hand, [1930?] (Box 5, Folder 99-111)
    Memoir by Corelli's life-long friend, with a Critical chapter by John Cuming Walters. Published as Memoirs of Marie Corelli. London [1930]